                                                    MACHINE LEARNING 
                           
                                                      WORKSHEET 4


1-(a)

2-(a)

3-(b)

4-(a)

5-(a)

6-(c)

7-(b)

8-(c)

Answer 10: Random forests overcome several problems with decision trees, including:

          Reduction in overfitting: by averaging several trees, there is a significantly lower risk of overfitting.

          Less variance: By using multiple trees, you reduce the chance of stumbling across a classifier that doesn’t perform well because of the relationship
          between the train and test data.

          As a consequence, in almost all cases, random forests are more accurate than decision trees.

Answer 11: Machine learning algorithm just sees number — if there is a vast difference in the range say few ranging in thousands and few ranging in the tens, and 
           it makes the underlying assumption that higher ranging numbers have superiority of some sort. So these more significant number starts playing a more
           decisive role while training the model.
           
           The machine learning algorithm works on numbers and does not know what that number represents. A weight of 10 grams and a price of 10 dollars represents 
           completely two different things — which is a no brainer for humans, but for a model as a feature, it treats both as same.

           The most common techniques of feature scaling are Normalization and Standardization.

Answer 12: Optimization refers to the task of minimizing/maximizing an objective function f(x) parameterized by x. In machine/deep learning terminology, it’s the task
           of minimizing the cost/loss function J(w) parameterized by the model’s parameters w ∈ R^d.

           Gradient Descent is the most common optimization algorithm in machine learning and deep learning. It is a first-order optimization algorithm. This means 
           it only takes into account the first derivative when performing the updates on the parameters. On each iteration, we update the parameters in the opposite
           direction of the gradient of the objective function J(w) w.r.t the parameters where the gradient gives the direction of the steepest ascent. The size of
           the step we take on each iteration to reach the local minimum is determined by the learning rate α. Therefore, we follow the direction of the slope
           downhill until we reach a local minimum.

Answe 13:  In the framework of imbalanced data-sets, accuracy is no longer a proper measure, since it does not distinguish between the numbers of correctly classified
           examples of different classes.

           A pair of evaluations metrics that are commonly used when there is a class imbalance are precision and recall. Precision is defined as the number of true 
           positives divided by the sum of true positives and false positives.

Answer 14: The F-score, also called the F1-score, is a measure of a model’s accuracy on a dataset. It is used to evaluate binary classification systems, which 
           classify examples into ‘positive’ or ‘negative’.
           
           The F-score is a way of combining the precision and recall of the model, and it is defined as the harmonic mean of the model’s precision and recall.
           
           The F-score is commonly used for evaluating information retrieval systems such as search engines, and also for many kinds of machine learning models, 
           in particular in natural language processing.

           F-score Formula

           The formula for the standard F1-score is the harmonic mean of the precision and recall. A perfect model has an F-score of 1.
           F1= 2(precision * recall / precision + recall)

Answer 15:  Most scikit-learn objects are either transformers or models.
            Transformers are for pre-processing before modeling. The Imputer class (like SimpleImputer for filling in missing values) and FeatureSelection classes
            in sklearn are an example of some transformers.

            Models are used to make predictions like Linear Regression model, Decision Tree model, Random Forest model etc. You will usually pre-process your data
            (with transformers) before putting it in a model.

            Now the usage of methods fit(), transform(), fit_transform() and predict() depend on the type of object.

For Transformers:
1. fit() - It is used for calculating the initial filling of parameters on the training data (like mean of the column values) and saves them as an internal objects
           state.
2. transform() - Use the above calculated values and return modified training data

3. fit_transform() - It joins above two steps. Internally, it just calls first fit() and then transform() on the same data.

For Models:
1. fit() - It calculates the parameters/weights on training data (e.g. parameters returned by coef() in case of Linear Regression) and saves them as an internal
           objects state.

2. predict() - Use the above calculated weights on test data to make the predictions

3. transform() - Cannot be used

4. fit_transform() - Cannot be used

